<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<debate>
<title>Switch</title>

<defs>
  <def id="angular_velocity">Angular velocity - The rate at which an object rotates about an axis, measured in radians per second (rad/s) and denoted by ω.</def>

  <def id="velocity_relation">Velocity relation - The equation ω = v/R, which relates the tangential (linear) speed v of a point on a rotating body to its angular velocity ω and the radius R of its circular path.</def>

  <def id="point_mass">Point mass - An idealized object with mass but no spatial extent, used to simplify analysis by ignoring rotation and internal structure.</def>

  <def id="rigid_body">Rigid body - An idealized solid object in which the distance between every pair of points remains constant, so it can rotate as well as translate.</def>

  <def id="tangent">Tangent - A straight line that touches a curve at exactly one point and points in the direction the curve is heading at that point.</def>

  <def id="radially">Radially - In the direction pointing toward or away from the center of a circular path.</def>

  <def id="tangentially">Tangentially - In the direction along the instantaneous velocity of an object moving on a curved path, i.e. perpendicular to the radial direction.</def>

  <def id="normal">Normal - Perpendicular to a surface or line at a given point.</def>

  <def id="positive_work">Positive work - Work done on an object when the applied force has a component in the same direction as the object's displacement, resulting in an increase in the object's kinetic energy.</def>

  <def id="constraint_force">Constraint force - A force exerted by a surface, track, or other boundary that restricts an object's motion to a particular path.</def>

  <def id="ke">Kinetic energy (KE) - The energy an object possesses due to its motion, equal to ½mv² for an object of mass m moving at speed v.</def>
</defs>

<question id="claim_0">
  A train car is freely coasting around a large circular track. It is then switched to a smaller circular track. How does its speed change? Assume no friction.

  <answer id="claim_1" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="No (main objection)">
    The speed stays the same if we model the car as a <a xdef="point_mass">point mass</a>. A small slowdown is possible if modeled as a <a xdef="rigid_body">rigid body</a>.
    <answer id="claim_2" speaker="D" honest_response="No (main objection)" dishonest_response="Yes">
      A ball on a string spins faster when pulled inward. The same principle applies when the car transitions to a tighter radius.
      <answer id="claim_3" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="Yes">The string does work because, as the ball spirals inward, its velocity has a radial component aligned with the tension.</answer>
      <answer id="claim_4" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="No (main objection)">
        The fixed frictionless track exerts only a force perpendicular to the car's velocity, so unlike the string it does no work.
        <answer id="claim_5" speaker="D" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="Yes">The curvature changes continuously along the connecting track, so the constraint force direction rotates.</answer>
        <answer id="claim_6" speaker="D" honest_response="No (main objection)" dishonest_response="Yes">
          This rotation means the force cannot remain perfectly perpendicular to velocity.
          <answer id="claim_7" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="No (secondary objection)">The car's velocity is <a xdef="tangent">tangent</a> to the track at every point. The constraint force is <a xdef="normal">normal</a> to the track, hence perpendicular to velocity.</answer>
          <answer id="claim_8" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="No (main objection)">
            At every instant, the force and velocity rotate together, maintaining perpendicularity even as curvature changes.
            <answer id="claim_9" speaker="D" honest_response="Yes but omits key info" dishonest_response="Yes">On a changing-curvature path, the constraint force adjusts in both magnitude and direction.</answer>
            <answer id="claim_10" speaker="D" honest_response="Yes but omits key info" dishonest_response="Yes">The centripetal acceleration behaves differently on the connecting track than it does on either circular section.</answer>
            <answer id="claim_11" speaker="D" honest_response="No (main objection)" dishonest_response="Yes">
              Therefore, you should reject <xref rid="claim_8"/>.
              <answer id="claim_12" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="No (secondary objection)">Force adjusting direction is what maintains perpendicularity; it rotates to stay normal as velocity rotates to stay tangent.</answer>
              <answer id="claim_13" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="Yes but omits key info">Centripetal force remains perpendicular to the velocity throughout, regardless of how its magnitude varies.</answer>
              <answer id="claim_14" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="No (main objection)">Therefore, you should reject <xref rid="claim_11"/>.</answer>
            </answer>
          </answer>
          <answer id="claim_15" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes">Therefore, you should reject <xref rid="claim_6"/>.</answer>
        </answer>
        <answer id="claim_16" speaker="D" dishonest_response="Yes">Therefore, you should reject <xref rid="claim_4"/>.</answer>
      </answer>
      <answer id="claim_17" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes">Therefore, you should reject <xref rid="claim_2"/>.</answer>
    </answer>
    <answer id="claim_18" speaker="D" honest_response="No (secondary objection)" dishonest_response="Yes">The connecting track provides a <a xdef="radially">radially</a> inward force that accelerates the car <a xdef="tangentially">tangentially</a>.</answer>
    <answer id="claim_19" speaker="D" dishonest_response="Yes">Therefore, you should reject <xref rid="claim_1"/>.</answer>
  </answer>
  <answer id="claim_20" speaker="D" honest_response="No (main objection)" dishonest_response="Yes">
    The speed increases whether we model the car as a <a xdef="point_mass">point mass</a> or as a <a xdef="rigid_body">rigid body</a>.
    <answer id="claim_21" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="No (main objection)">
      On a frictionless track, the rails' <a xdef="constraint_force">constraint force</a> does no work, so <a xdef="ke">kinetic energy (KE)</a> is conserved and speed cannot increase.
      <answer id="claim_22" speaker="D" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="Yes">If true that the rails do no work, then a point-mass car would not lose speed on the smaller track.</answer>
      <answer id="claim_23" speaker="D" honest_response="No (main objection)" dishonest_response="Yes">
        But if KE is conserved (Debater A Argument 1 Claim 1) and the rails do no work, then there should be no slowdown on a frictionless track for a rigid body model, contra Debater A Opening.
        <answer id="claim_24" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="Yes">A rigid body has both translational and rotational KE; a point mass has only translational.</answer>
        <answer id="claim_25" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="No (main objection)">
          On a tighter track, rotational KE increases at the expense of translational KE.
          <answer id="claim_26" speaker="D" honest_response="No (main objection)" dishonest_response="Yes">
            This is only true if we assume the body is constrained to yaw with the track curvature (rigid link between axles and body), an unwarranted assumption.
            <answer id="claim_27" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="Yes but omits key info">Both axles are constrained to the rails, so the body's orientation is pinned by the chord between the two axle positions.</answer>
            <answer id="claim_28" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="Yes but omits key info">On a curved section this geometrically forces the body to yaw as it advances.</answer>
            <answer id="claim_29" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="No (main objection)">
              Therefore, you should reject <xref rid="claim_26"/>.
              <answer id="claim_30" speaker="D" honest_response="Yes but omits key info" dishonest_response="Yes">A car whose axles are rigidly fixed parallel to the body cannot roll without slipping on a curved track.</answer>
              <answer id="claim_31" speaker="D" honest_response="No (secondary objection)" dishonest_response="Yes">The curvature differs at the front and rear contact points on the connecting track, with consequences for yaw and speed.</answer>
              <answer id="claim_32" speaker="D" honest_response="No (main objection)" dishonest_response="Yes">Therefore, you should reject <xref rid="claim_29"/>.</answer>
            </answer>
          </answer>
          <answer id="claim_33" speaker="D" honest_response="No (secondary objection)" dishonest_response="Yes">We can't justifiably force such exact yaw, so total KE stays translational and speed does not fall.</answer>
          <answer id="claim_34" speaker="D" dishonest_response="Yes">Therefore, you should reject <xref rid="claim_25"/>.</answer>
        </answer>
        <answer id="claim_35" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes">Therefore, you should reject <xref rid="claim_23"/>.</answer>
      </answer>
      <answer id="claim_36" speaker="D" dishonest_response="Yes">Therefore, you should reject <xref rid="claim_21"/>.</answer>
    </answer>
    <answer id="claim_37" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes" dishonest_response="No (secondary objection)">There is no mechanism on a fixed frictionless track to add energy to the car.</answer>
    <answer id="claim_38" speaker="H" honest_response="Yes">Therefore, you should reject <xref rid="claim_20"/>.</answer>
  </answer>
</question>
</debate>
